A Finding Aid to the Takis Efstathiou papers regarding Ynez Johnston, 1954-2004, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Takis Efstathiou papers regarding Ynez Johnston
1954-2004
Archives of American Art
Efstathiou, Takis, 1944-
AAA.efsttaki
Archival Resource Key
0.8 Linear feet
This small collection of papers of New York City art dealer Takis Efstathiou papers regarding Los Angeles artist Ynez Johnston measure 0.8 linear feet and date from 1954-2004. The papers include correspondence with Johnston and with institutions regarding Johnston's work and career, a few business records from the Ericson Gallery (owned by Efstathiou), printed material about Johnston, and photographic material of Johnston's artwork and of the artist at home, in her studio, and of the exhibition opening organized by Efstathiou at Ericson Gallery in 1979.
Scope and Contents
This small collection of papers of New York City art dealer Takis Efstathiou papers regarding Los Angeles artist Ynez Johnston measure 0.8 linear feet and date from 1954-2004. The papers include correspondence with Johnston and with institutions regarding Johnston's work and career, a few business records from the Ericson Gallery (owned by Efstathiou), printed material about Johnston, and photographic material of Johnston's artwork and of the artist at home, in her studio, and of the exhibition opening organized by Efstathiou at Ericson Gallery in 1979.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as four series
Series 1: Correspondence, 1974-1999 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Business Records, circa 1975-1979 (2 folders; Box 1)
Series 3: Printed Material, 1954-2004 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 4: Photographic Material, circa 1977-1999 (0.2 linear feet; Box 2)
Biographical / Historical
Takis Efstathiou (1944- ) is a New York City art dealer for the work of Ynez Johnston. He was director of Tchernov Gallery in 1973, and, in 1977, opened the Ericson gallery on 74th Street and Madison Avenue, before becoming a private dealer in 1986 working under the name PTE Fine Arts. Ynez Johnston is a printmaker, painter, sculptor, and instructor who lives and works in Southern California.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Related Materials
Also found in the Archives of American Art are the scattered records of Efstathiou's private art dealing business PTE Fine Arts.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to the Archives of American Art by Takis Efstathiou in 2016.
Art dealers -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- California -- Los Angeles; Photographs; Printmakers -- California -- Los Angeles; Women artists; Artists' studios -- California; Johnston, Ynez, 1920-; Ericson Gallery
- Correspondence, 1974-1999; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence dates from 1974-1999 and includes dozens of letters to and from Ynez Johnston regarding her work, exhibitions, and career. There is also a folder of correspondence between Efstathiou and various institutions concerning exhibitions, publications, loans, and gifts of Johnston's work.
  - Ynez Johnston, 1974-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Institutional Correspondence, 1977-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Business Records, circa 1975-1979; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders Box 1
  Business records date from circa 1975-1979 and include addresses, business receipts, and inventory lists related to the operation of the Ericson Gallery.
  - Addresses and Receipts, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Inventory Lists, circa 1975-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Printed Material, 1954-2004; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Printed material dates from 1954-2004 and consists of announcements, press releases, clippings, curricula vitae, a monograph, and other publications related to or featuring the work of Ynez Johnston. Efstathiou was consulted on Johnston's exhibition history for the monograph by Gerald Norland. Correspondence between Efstathiou and Norland is in series 1.
  - Announcements and Press Releases, 1966-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1962-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Curricula Vitae for Ynez Johnston, circa 1979; circa 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ynez Johnston Monograph by Gerald Norland, 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Publications, 1954-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Transcribed Reviews and Essays regarding Ynez Johnston, circa 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Photographic Material, circa 1977-1999; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Photographic material dates from circa 1977-1999 and includes photographic prints, negatives, slides, and transparencies of Johnston's artwork. There are also slides from visits that Efstathiou made to Johnson's studio in Los Angeles in the late 1970s and prints from Johnston's exhibition opening at Ericson Gallery in 1979.
  - Artwork, circa 1977-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Ynez Johnston and Others, circa 1977-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)